Finding Aid for Penn Central Transportation Company Records 1835-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Penn Central Transportation Company Records
1835-1981
1835-1960
Penn Central Transportation Company
Records of railroad companies, mainly Michigan lines, absorbed with the merger of the New York Central Railroad Company and the Pennsylvania Railroad Company into the Penn Central Transportation Company.
87400 BB.1 Bb.1
273 linear feet
144 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Penn Central Transportation Company records (donor no. 7310 ) include the records of hundreds of companies that were initially independent but were eventually absorbed by the New York Central Railroad Company or the Pennsylvania Railroad Company. The records were acquired by the Bentley Library as part of the Penn Central Railroad Appraisal Project. This project was funded by the National Historical Publications and Records Commission and lasted from April 1, 1984 to October 15, 1986. The project's team of archivists appraised the records of Penn Central and distributed them to seven repositories: the Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission, the Hagley Museum and Library, the New York Public Library, the New Jersey State Archives, Temple University, Penn State University, and the Bentley Historical Library.
The records of the Pennsylvania Railroad were divided among the seven repositories on a roughly geographical basis, with the Bentley Library receiving records of all companies that were subsidiaries of the Grand Rapids and Indiana Railroad, a subsystem of the Pennsylvania Railroad. About one-third of the Grand Rapids and Indiana subsidiaries' lines ran within the boundaries of Michigan.
The New York Central Railroad records were distributed in a similar fashion, with the Bentley receiving records of the Michigan Central Railroad, the Lake Shore and Michigan Southern Railroad, and their subsidiaries.
The Bentley also received the records of the Ann Arbor Railroad, an independently-operated company in which the Pennsylvania Railroad held a majority interest, and the Detroit, Toledo and Ironton Railroad. The Ann Arbor Railroad was formed in 1895 through the reorganization of the Toledo, Ann Arbor, and North Michigan Railroad. The Detroit, Toledo and Ironton Railroad was created in 1905 through a series of consolidations of Ohio and Michigan railroad lines. Henry Ford purchased the Detroit, Toledo and Ironton in 1920 and sold it in 1929 to Pennroad, a holding company that was owned principally by Pennsylvania Railroad stockholders. The Detroit, Toledo and Ironton continued to be operated separately, but its purchase by Pennroad assured that the Pennsylvania Railroad's interests would be protected.
The record group is open for research.
The Pennsylvania Railroad Company was formed in 1846 and expanded rapidly in the 1860s and 1870s, eventually controlling over 800 corporations. The New York Central Railroad Company was organized in 1853 and merged with the Hudson River Railroad in 1869 to form the New York Central and Hudson River Railroad; in 1914 the name was again changed to the New York Central Railroad Company.
The Penn Central Transportation Company was formed in 1968 through the merger of the Pennsylvania and New York Central Railroads. The company did not prosper and went bankrupt in 1970. The company was reorganized in 1971 with the help of the Federal Government and the creation of the National Railroad Passenger Corporation (AMTRAK) which assumed long distance passenger service and in 1976 with the Consolidated Rail Corporation (Conrail) which took over the viable parts of Penn Central and five other bankrupt rail lines. Penn Central was reorganized as the Penn Central Corporation in 1978; it liquidated most of its rail subsidiaries and property and became a general holding company with subsidiaries in energy, electronics, equipment, manufacture, and real estate.
The Penn Central Transportation Company records date from 1835 to 1981. They measure 273 linear feet plus 144 oversize volumes. Included are 28 reels of microfilm received with the paper records. The records are divided into five subgroups: Ann Arbor Railroad Company; Detroit, Toledo and Ironton Railroad Company; New York Central Railroad Company; Pennsylvania Railroad Company; and Miscellaneous Railroad Records.
Summary Contents List
Ann Arbor Railroad Company [boxes 1-59; 269-271; 274] Administrative Records [Boxes 1-7; 269] Annual Reports [box 1] Minutes: Board of Directors and Executive Committee [boxes 2-7; 269; 274] Financial Records [boxes 7-16; 270-271] Legal and Other Records [boxes 16-17; 271] Labor Relations Files [boxes 18-59] Ann Arbor Railroad Company: Subsidiaries [boxes 61-66; 272; 274]
Detroit, Toledo and Ironton Railroad Company [boxes 66-69; 274-275]
New York Central Railroad Company New York Central Records (prior to November 1, 1869) [box 70] New York Central and Hudson River Railroad Company (November 1869-December 1914) Annual Reports [box 70] Minutes of Board of Directors and Executive Committee [box 60] New York Central Records (following name change from New York Central and Hudson River Railroad Company in December 1914) Annual Meeting of Shareowners: Reports [box 71] Annual Reports [boxes 60, 71-72] Reports to Interstate Commerce Commission [boxes 72-75] Annual Reports (Green Books) [boxes 254-267] New York Central Railroad Company: Subsidiaries [boxes 60, 76-154; 276-290; oversize volumes 1-75 and 142] Lake Shore and Michigan Southern Railway Company [boxes 118-120; oversize volumes 24-27, 48] Michigan Central Railroad Company [boxes 126-140, 287-289; oversize volumes 28-35, 37-47]
Pennsylvania Railroad Company Histories [boxes 60, 155-157, 183] Annual Reports: Pennsylvania Railroad and Controlled Lines East and West of Pittsburgh [boxes 172-182] Bylaws and Organization [box 183] General Manager - Western Region [boxes 184-191] Miscellaneous [box 183] Superintendent - Toledo Division [boxes 192-195] Vice-President and General Counsel [boxes 195-197] Pennsylvania Railroad Company: Subsidiaries [boxes 198-247; 290; oversize volumes 76-141] Grand Rapids and Indiana Railroad/Railway Company [boxes 213-229; oversize volumes 94-128, 135-141]
Miscellaneous Railroad Records [boxes 248-253; 290]
The nature of the records of the Pennsylvania Railroad and the New York Central Railroad reflects the recent history of the two companies. When the Penn Central Transportation Company was formed in 1968, the offices of New York Central--the junior merger partner--were dismantled and only a small percentage of records retained. Therefore, the extant New York Central records consist almost entirely of minutes and account books of a routine nature. By contrast, records of the Pennsylvania Railroad were relatively undisturbed by the merger and are today richer and more varied than those of the New York Central. The Penn Central records are most useful for their documentation of the growth of the railroad industry. They depict an industry in constant flux due to the opportunities for success offered by a burgeoning industry and the intense competition among railroads that resulted. A single volume of records often contains minutes of two or more railroads, reflecting either the failure of the original company or its takeover by or merger with another company.
Besides documenting the history of individual railroads and of the railroad industry as a whole, the Penn Central records are a good source on the economic and commercial development of Michigan and neighboring states, and provide insight into the rise and decline of various towns along the railroad. Minutes of New York Central subsidiaries, for example, contain discussions of negotiations with town officials over the proposed construction of tracks, bridges, depots, and the like. Similarly, the locality files in the Superintendent--Toledo Division series of the Pennsylvania Railroad records consist of correspondence and memoranda regarding improvements to, or the abandonment of, stations in small towns in Michigan, Indiana, and Ohio. This series also contains substantial correspondence files on Toledo, Detroit, and Grand Rapids.
Labor and social historians will find the Penn Central records useful in illuminating the lives of workers and in documenting relations between management and workers. More than 40 feet of labor relations files of the Ann Arbor Railroad include agreements between the company and unions, grievances, petitions concerning work rules and pay, wage and hour schedules, and circular letters. There are small series of labor relations files of other companies scattered throughout the collection. Researchers will also find information on the workplace and working conditions in the locality files of the Superintendent--Toledo Division series of the Pennsylvania Railroad; these files contain, for example, memoranda concerning clubrooms and sleeping quarters for workers in city depots.
There is very little technical material in the Penn Central records; photographs are likewise scarce. The most notable exceptions are in the car ferry files, found in three subseries of the Pennsylvania Railroad records: General Manager--Western Region, Vice-President and General Counsel, and Subsidiaries: Mackinac Transportation Company. The car ferry files include maps, plans, specifications, blueprints, and some photographs.
A large portion of the collection consists of records of small railroads that ran through Michigan or were based in Michigan. Records of these companies are brief, often including nothing more than articles of incorporation, a few pages or a volume or two of minutes, and perhaps some annual reports and financial records. Although many of these railroads were subsidiaries of either the Michigan Central Railroad, the Lake Shore and Michigan Southern Railroad, or the Grand Rapids and Indiana Railroad, they have been filed under the parent company of which the sub-system was a part (New York Central, Pennsylvania, or Ann Arbor Railroad) to promote ease of access. Thus, for example, records of the Canada Southern Bridge Company, a subsidiary of Michigan Central Railroad, are filed under New York Central Railroad, the parent company of Michigan Central. Researchers uncertain of the parentage of a particular railroad should look in the subsidiaries section of the contents list under Ann Arbor, New York Central, and Pennsylvania Railroads. The railroads in each of these subsidiaries sections are arranged in alphabetical order.
Brief histories of individual railroads can be found in the "Green Books"--the annual reports of the New York Central Railroad Company and its subsidiaries. There are several published histories of the Pennsylvania Railroad in boxes 183 and boxes 155-157 and on microfilm in box 60.
A card file giving the date of incorporation, name changes, and parentage of subsidiaries of the Michigan Central Railroad, Lake Shore and Michigan Southern Railroad, and the Grand Rapids and Indiana Railroad has been photocopied and can be found in box 1 of the collection. This folder also contains a list of records in the Public Archives of Canada of Grand Trunk and Great Western Railway system properties in the United States. Finally, there is a section of Aids, Gifts, Grants and Donations to Railroads Including Outline of Development and Successions in Titles to Railroads in Michigan by the Michigan Railroads Commission (1919).
Information in this finding aid concerning the histories of the various railroads was drawn from the collection itself, from sources compiled by the project archivists, and from the following published sources: William Frederick Dunbar All Aboard! A History of Railroads in Michigan (Grand Rapids, Michigan: William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company, 1969) and Henry E. Riggs, The Ann Arbor Railroad Fifty Years Ago (Ann Arbor Railroad Company, 1947?)
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Railroad Company.; Bay View, Little Traverse and Mackinac Rail Road Company.; Business records.; Canada Southern Bridge Company.; Canada Southern Railway Company.; Caro and Lake Huron Railroad Company.; Chicago River and Indiana Railroad Company.; Detroit and Bay City Railroad Company.; Detroit Manufacturers' Railroad Company.; Detroit, Monroe & Toledo Short Line Railway.; Detroit River Tunnel Company.; Detroit Terminal Railroad Company.; Detroit, Toledo, and Ironton Railroad.; Detroit Union Railroad, Depot & Station Company.; Ferries--Great Lakes.; Grand Rapids and Indiana Railroad Company.; Jackson, Lansing and Saginaw Railroad Company.; Railroads--Michigan--Employees.; Lake Shore & Michigan Southern Railway.; Mackinac Transportation Company.; Manistique and Lake Superior Railroad Company.; Manistique, Marquette and Northern Railroad Company.; Michigan Air Line Railroad Company.; Michigan Central Railroad Company.; Michigan Southern and Northern Indiana Railroad Company.; Muskegon, Grand Rapids and Indiana Railroad Company.; New York Central and Hudson River Railroad Company.; New York Central Railroad Company.; Pennsylvania Railroad.; Railroads--United States.; Railroads--Michigan.; Traverse City Railroad Company.; Western Transit Company.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ferries.; Interiors.; Manistee (Mich.); Milwaukee (Wis.); Railroads--Wisconsin--Milwaukee.; Railroads--Michigan--Manistee.; Wisconsin and Michigan Transportation Company.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Ann Arbor Railroad Company, 1896-1964; 67 linear feet
  This subgroup is divided into administrative records, financial records, legal and other records, labor relations files, and records of subsidiaries. Administrative and financial records are arranged alphabetically by type of material, labor relations files by file number.
  Records of the parent company include annual reports for the years 1910 to 1963; minutes of meetings of the board of directors and executive committee, 1910 to 1960; financial records; reports to the Interstate Commerce Commission; legal records; and various other reports and studies. The bulk of the records--42 feet--consists of labor relations files dating primarily from the 1920s to 1960. These files contain contracts and agreements, complaints, and claims regarding wages, hours, rules, and regulations for various groups of railroad workers. A card file in box 57 indexes and summarizes circular letters sent out by the Bureau of Information of the Eastern Railways from the 1930s to the 1960s.
  In addition to the records of the Ann Arbor Railroad there are fragmentary records of five of its subsidiaries: the Ann Arbor Boat Company; Manistique and Lake Superior Railroad Company; Manistique, Marquette and Northern Railroad Company; Menominee and St. Paul Railway Company; and Wabash Radio Corporation. These records range from annual reports and minutes to labor relations files, balance sheets, and reports to the Michigan Board of Assessors.
  - Annual Reports
    - 1910-1912, 3 items (Box 1)
    - 1913-1927, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1928-1963, 40 items (Box 1)
  - Minutes: Board of Directors and Executive Committee
    - April 1910-July 6, 1916, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - July 12, 1916-April 19, 1924, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - April 29, 1924-May 15, 1928, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - May 29, 1928-May 22, 1934, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - June 12, 1934-November 17, 1943, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - January 20, 1944-February 17, 1949, 1 volumes (Box 4)
    - March 17, 1949-April 17, 1952, 1 volumes (Box 4)
    - May 20, 1952-December 15, 1955, 1 volumes (Box 5)
    - January 19, 1956-December 18, 1958, 1 volumes (Box 5)
    - February 19, 1959-April 21, 1960 (Box 6)
    - May 17, 1960-July 19, 1962, 2 copies (Box 269)
    - September 20, 1962-September 26, 1963, 1 volumes (Box 269)
    - 1967-1971 (Box 274)
  - Minutes: Stockholders, 1964-1973; 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 274)
  - Minutes, Extracts of Board of Directors' Meetings
    - 1942-1957, 15 folders (Box 6)
    - 1958-1960, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Financial Records
    - Balance Sheets, General
      - 1920-1925 (Box 7)
      - 1933-1934, 2 volumes (Box 7)
      - 1936, 1939-1940; 3 volumes (Box 8)
      - 1941, 1943-1948; 3 volumes (Box 9)
      - 1949-1951, 1953-1958; 3 volumes (Box 10)
      - 1957-1961, 1 volumes (Box 11)
      - Master Copies, 1948-1951; 1 volumes (Box 11)
      - Pencil Copies, 1948-1951; 1 volumes (Box 11)
      - Monthly Report, 1944-1958; 1 volumes (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous Financial Records
      - Comptrollers Files: Income and Dividends, 1930-1960 (Box 12)
      - Equipment Rosters, 1915; 1942 (Box 12)
      - Financial Statements, 1949-1963; 1 volumes (Box 12)
    - Reports to the Interstate Commerce Commission
      - 1904-1907, 4 volumes (Box 12)
      - 1912-1915, 4 volumes (Box 13)
      - 1927-1932, 3 folders; 4 volumes (Box 13)
      - 1933-1947, 15 volumes (Box 14)
      - 1948-1958, 11 volumes (Box 15)
      - 1959-1960, 2 volumes (Box 16)
      - 1961-1976, 16 volumes (Box 270)
    - Miscellaneous Reports
      - Reports to the Michigan Board of Assessors
        - 1944-1960 (Box 16)
        - 1961-1977, 17 volumes (Box 271)
      - Revenue Traffic Reports, 1945-1959; 1 volumes (Box 16)
      - Roadway Depreciation Study, 1940; 1 volumes (Box 16)
      - Income account and analysis of income, 1956-1959 (Box 271)
      - Symbol system for additions and betterments to equipment, 1959-1963 (Box 271)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 271)
  - Legal and other Records
    - Court Orders, 1931-1943; 4 volumes (Box 17)
    - Receivership Records, 1931-1943; 2 volumes (Box 17)
    - Contract with Monroe & Toledo RR, 1896 (Box 17)
    - Car Ferry Schedule, 1964 (Box 17)
  - Labor Relations Files
    - Numbered Files
      - A500 Ann Arbor Railroad Company: General, 1926-1951 (Box 18)
      - A501 Mileage: Engineers, 1930-1953 (Box 18)
      - A503 Wage and Hours Schedules and Agreements:
        - General, 1926-1957 (Box 18)
        - 1) Firemen and Engineers, 1943-1958 (Box 19)
        - 1) Firemen and Engineers, 1936-1960 (Box 20)
        - 1) Tables of Standard Basic Daily Rates, 1915-1955 (Box 20)
        - 1) Firemen and Engineers, 1945-1947 (Box 21)
        - 1-1) Firemen and Engineers, 1941-1950 (Box 21)
        - 1-1) Firemen, 1947-1956 (Box 22)
        - 1-2)Firemen and Engineers, 1943-1953 (Box 22)
        - 2) Conductors and Trainmen, 1900; 1922-1960 (Box 23)
        - 2) Conductors and Trainmen, 1949-1961 (Box 24)
        - 2) Yardmen, 1942; 1951-1959 (Box 25)
        - 3) Clerks, 1955 (Box 25)
        - 3) Clerks, 1945-1960 (Box 26)
        - 4) Signalmen, 1943-1960 (Box 26)
        - 5) Telegraphers, 1946-1960 (Box 27)
        - 6) Shop Crafts, 1946-1961 (Box 27)
        - 6) Shop Crafts, 1951-1954 (Box 28)
        - 8) Linemen, 1951-1960 (Box 28)
        - 12) Yard Crews: Rule changes, 1941 (Box 28)
        - 13/14) Engine and Train Service Employees: Reports, 1941 (Box 28)
        - 17) Selected Employee Groups, 1941 (Box 28)
        - 24) Train Dispatchers, 1946-1950 (Box 28)
        - 25) Patrolmen, 1947-1956 (Box 28)
        - 26) Pursers and Radio Operators, 1946-1960 (Box 29)
        - 27) Mechanical Department Foremen, 1946-1960 (Box 29)
        - 28) Yardmasters, 1946-1960 (Box 29)
        - 28) Yardmasters, 1947-1958 (Box 30)
        - 29/30) Non-operating Employees, 1947-1948 (Box 30)
        - 31) Maintenance of Way Supervisors (subordinate officials), 1949-1960 (Box 30)
        - 32) Non-operating Employees, 1950-1957 (Box 30)
        - 32) Non-operating Employees, 1948-1955 (Box 31)
        - 34) Fifteen Cooperating Railway Labor Organizations (Request for Wage Increases), 1952-1953 (Box 31)
        - 34) Fifteen Cooperating Railway Labor Organizations (Request for Wage Increases), 1952-1953 (Box 32)
        - 35) Non-operating Railway Labor Organizations, 1953-1955 (Box 32)
        - 36) Non-operating Railway Labor Organizations, 1955-1956 (Box 33)
        - 38) Railway Labor Executives Association, 1958-1960 (Box 33)
      - A504 Wage Agreements: Conductors and Trainmen, 1926-1930 (Box 33)
      - A505 Vacations: Agent-Telegrapher, Non-operating Employees, Train and Engine Service Employees, 1942-1959 (Box 33)
      - A507 Deadheading, 1931; 1953; 1960 (Box 34)
        - 1) Manning and handling crews on football specials, 1960 (Box 34)
        - 2) Basis for payment for deadheading to and from baggage master service, 1941 (Box 34)
      - A509 Guarantees, 1929-1960 (Box 34)
      - A511 Leaves of Absence, 1937-1957
        - 1) Compensation, 1940-1948 (Box 34)
        - 3) Compensation, 1940-1948 (Box 34)
        - 4) Clerks: Leaves of Absence for Military Service, 1945-1956 (Box 34)
        - 5) Maintenance of Way Workers: Leaves of Absence for Military Service, 1956 (Box 34)
        - 6) Enginemen: Leaves of Absence for Military Service, 1945 (Box 34)
        - 8) Telegraphers: Leaves of Absence for Military Service, 1941-1947 (Box 34)
        - 10) Seniority Status of Employees working in Outside Industry or Government Service, 1940; 1951 (Box 34)
        - 11) Shop Crafts, Linemen, Sheet Metal Workers, 1942-1954 (Box 34)
        - 12) Work or Wreck Train Service, 1939-1959 (Box 34)
      - A514 Claims of Engineers; Preparatory and Inspection Time; National Railroad Adjustment Board Cases, 1939-1950 (Box 35)
      - A515 Marine Employees and Engineers (Beneficial Association; Installing Diesel Power), 1934-1938; 1960
        - 1) Relief Days for Pursers on Lake Michigan Car Ferries, 1937 (Box 35)
        - 2) Maritime Labor Boards, 1951 (Box 35)
        - 3) Claims of Marine Employees, Licensed Deck Officers, and Seafarer's International Union; Filling Vacancies of Marine Employees, 1955-1959 (Box 35)
        - 7) Pay During Suspensions and Holidays, 1958-1960 (Box 35)
      - A516 Wage Reductions (Outside Industries; Conference Committee of Managers), 1934-1940 (Box 35)
      - A516 Wage Reductions (Officers and Excepted Positions; Canadian National and Canadian Pacific Railways), 1931-1947 (Box 36)
        - 01) Conductors and Trainmen, 1938 (Box 36)
        - 02) Engineers and Firemen, 1938 (Box 36)
        - 03) Clerks, 1938 (Box 36)
        - 04) Telegraphers, 1938 (Box 36)
        - 05) Dispatchers, 1938-1939 (Box 36)
        - 06) Maintenance of Way, 1938 (Box 36)
        - 07) Signalmen, 1938 (Box 36)
        - 08) Shopmen, 1938 (Box 36)
        - 09) Marine Engineers, 1938 (Box 36)
        - 10) Masters, Mates, Pilots, 1938 (Box 36)
        - 11) Marine Cooks and Stewards, 1938 (Box 36)
        - 12) Marine Firemen, Oilers, Sailor's Union, 1938 (Box 36)
        - 1) Trainmen and Enginemen, 1931-1934 (Box 36)
        - 2) Clerks, 1931-1934 (Box 36)
        - 3) Telegraphers, 1931-1934 (Box 36)
        - 4) Maintenance of Way Workers, 1931-1934 (Box 36)
        - 7) Dispatchers, 1930-1934 (Box 36)
        - 8) Marine Employees, 1931-1934 (Box 36)
        - 9) Shopmen, 1931-1934 (Box 36)
      - A519 Mileage Claims: Engineers and Firemen, 1947-1960 (Box 36)
      - A520 Rates of Pay
        - 1) History of Standard Rules Governing Conductors and Trainmen in Yard Service (various agreements), 1950-1955 (Box 37)
        - 2) Engineers, Firemen, Hostlers (Box 37)
        - 3) Clerks, 1920-1959 (Box 37)
        - 4) Approving Pay Rates, 1939-1957 (Box 37)
        - 6) Claim of Engineer, 1950 (Box 37)
        - 7) Shop Watchmen, 1941 (Box 37)
        - 8) Warehouse Foremen, 1941 (Box 37)
        - 10) Yardmasters, 1956 (Box 37)
        - 11) "The Earnings and Employment of Seamen on U.S. Flag Ships,", 1958 (Box 37)
      - A521 Signalmen, 1932-1954
        - 1) Signal Foremen on Union Pacific--brought within terms of "employees" under Railway Labor Act, 1936 (Box 37)
        - 2) Signal Maintainers: Sunday Work, 1937 (Box 37)
        - 4) Five-Day Week, 1937-1943 (Box 37)
      - A522 Six-Hour Day, 1932-1937
        - 1) General Office Forces, 1932 (Box 37)